<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired in the visitation, in the firste yere of the raigne of our moste dread soueraigne lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, &amp; Ireland, Quene, defendour of the faith, &amp;c., anno 1559</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4662</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23709640</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23709640</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1832:40)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired in the visitation, in the firste yere of the raigne of our moste dread soueraigne lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, &amp; Ireland, Quene, defendour of the faith, &amp;c., anno 1559</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted at London in Powles Church yarde by Richard Iugge and Iohn Cawood ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1561?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B³.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26824:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>Articles to be enquired in the viſitation, in the firſte yere of the raigne of our moſte dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lady, Elizabeth by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, and Ireland, Quene, defendour of the faith. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Anno. 1559.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26824:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26824:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <head>ARTICLES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſt, whether any Parſon, Vicar,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Reſidencie.</note> or Curate, be reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t continually vpon his Benefice, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng his duetie in preaching, reding and duelye mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrynge the holye Sacramentes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Falſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</note>Item, whether in theyr Churches and Chappelles, all Images, Shrynes, all Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Candelſtickes, Trindelles, or rolles of war, pictures, payntynges, and all other monumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of fayned and falſe miracles, pylgrymages, idolatrye, and ſuperſtition, be remoued, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhed, and deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Lordes prayer.</note>Item, whether they do not euery Holydaye when they haue no Sermon, immediatly after the Goſpell, openly, playnely, and diſtinctly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to theyr paryſhyoners in the Pulpitte, the Lordes prayer, the beliefe, and the tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes in Englyſhe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> To bryng vp youth.</note>Item, whether they do charge fathers and mothers, maiſters, and gouernours of youth, to bryng them vp in ſome vertuous ſtudye and occupation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26824:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Curates.</note> whether ſuche beneficed men as be lawfully abſent from theyr benefices, do leaue theyr cures to a rude and vnlearned Parſon, and not to an honeſt wel learned and expert Curate whiche can and wyll teache you holeſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Redyng the Scriptures.</note>Item, whether they do diſcourage any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from readyng of any part of the Byble, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Latin or Englyſh, and do not rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and exhort euery perſon to read the ſame at conuenient tymes, as the very lyuely worde of God, and the ſpeciall foode of mans ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>7.</hi> Tauernes and games.</note>Item, whether Parſons, Vicars, Curates, and other miniſters, be common haunters and reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to Tauernes or Alehouſes, geuyng them ſelues to drynkyng, ryotyng, and playing at vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful games, and do not occupy them ſelues in the readyng or hearynge of ſome part of holye Scripture, or in ſome other godly exercyſe.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>8.</hi> Preachers.</note> whether they haue admitted any man to preache in theyr cures, not beyng lawefully licenſed therunto, or haue bene licenſed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyngly.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>9</hi> Superſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> whether they vſe to declare to theyr pariſhioners any thyng to the extollyng or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng forth of vayne and ſuperſtitious religion, pilgrimages, reliques, or ymages, or lyghtyng
<pb facs="tcp:26824:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->of candelles, kyſſyng, knelyng, deckyng of the ſame ymages.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> Regiſter.</note> whether they haue one booke or Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter kept, wherein they wryte the daye of euery weddyng, chryſtenyng, and burying.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>11.</hi> Obedience.</note> whether they haue exhorted the people to obedience to the Quenes Maieſtie, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and to charitie and loue one to another.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>12.</hi> The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>Item, whether they haue admonyſhed theyr pariſhioners, that they ought not to preſume to receiue the Sacrament of the body and bloud of Chriſt before they can perfectly the Lordes pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the articles of the fayth, and the .x. commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes in Englyſhe.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>13.</hi> Hoſpitalitie.</note> whether they be reſident vpon theyr benefices, and kepe hoſpitalitie or no. And if they be abſent and kepe no hoſpitalitie, whether they do relieue theyr pariſhioners, and what they geue them.</p>
            <p>Item, whether proprietaries, Parſons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>14.</hi> Reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, and clarkes, hauyng Churches, chappels, or manſions, do kepe theyr chauncels, rectories, Vicarages, and all other houſes appertaynyng to them, in due reparations.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>15.</hi> Prayer in Englyſhe.</note>Item, whether they do counſayle or moue theyr pariſhioners rather to praye in a tounge not knowen, then in Englyſhe, or put theyr
<pb facs="tcp:26824:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->truſt in any certayne numbre of prayers, as in ſaying ouer a numbre of Beades,<note place="margin">Beades.</note> or other lyke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>16.</hi> Diffamed perſons.</note>Item, whether they haue receaued any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the communion, beyng openly knowen to be out of charitie with theyr neighbours, or dyffamed with anye notorious cryme, and not refourmed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>17.</hi> Poore mens boxe.</note>Item, whether they haue prouided and haue a ſtronge cheſt for the poore mens boxe, and ſet and faſtened the ſame in a place of the Churche moſt conuenient.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>18.</hi> Teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> whether they haue dil<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>igently called vpon, exhorted and moued theyr paryſhioners, and eſpecially when they make theyr teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to geue to the ſayd poore mens boxe, and to beſtowe that vpon the poore,<note place="margin">Poore mens boxe.</note> whiche they were wonte to beſtowe vpon pilgrimages, pardons, trentalles, and vpon other like blind deuocions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>19.</hi> Sycke. Buryall.</note>Item, whether they haue denyed to viſite the ſicke, or burye the deade, beynge brought to the Churche.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>20.</hi> Symonye.</note> whether they haue bought theyr be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, or come to them by fraude, guyle, deceit, or ſymonye.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>21.</hi> Adulterers.</note> whether they haue geuen open moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to theyr pariſhioners, to detect and preſent
<pb facs="tcp:26824:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->to theyr Ordinary, all adulterers and fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, and ſuch men as haue two wiues liuyng, within theyr paryſhes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>22.</hi> Churche goodes.</note>Item, whether they haue monyſhed theyr pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners openly, that they ſhould not ſel, geue, nor otherwyſe alienate anye of theyr Churche goodes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>23.</hi> Many Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices.</note>Item, whether they or any of them do kepe mo benefices and other Eccleſiaſticall promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then they ought to do, not hauyng ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent licences and diſpenſations thereunto, and howe many they be, and theyr names.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>24.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion.</note> whether they miniſter the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion any otherwyſe, then onely after ſuche fourme and maner as it is ſet forth by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aucthoritie of the Quenes Maieſtie, and the parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>25.</hi> Letters of the word or preachyng.</note>Item, whether you know any perſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your paryſhe, or els where, that is a letter of the worde of God to be read in Englyſhe, or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely preached in place and times conuenient.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>26.</hi> Goers out of the Church.</note>Item, whether in the tyme of the Letanye, or any other common prayer, in the tyme of the Sermon or Homelye, and when the Prieſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Scriptures to the pariſhioners, anye perſon haue departed out of the Churche, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſte and neceſſarye cauſe, or diſturbe the
<pb facs="tcp:26824:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->Miniſter otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>27.</hi> Church mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</note>Item, whether the money commyng and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of any cattell or other moueable ſtockes of the Church, and mony geuen and bequeathed to the fyndyng of torches, lyghtes, tapers, or lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, not payde out of any landes, haue not ben employed to the poore mens cheſte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>28.</hi> Kepers of the Church money.</note>Item, who hath the ſayd ſtockes and money in theyr handes, and what be theyr names.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>29.</hi> Contempt of Prieſtes.</note>Item, whether anye indiſcrete perſons do vncharitably contemne and abuſe Prieſtes and Miniſters of the Churche.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>30.</hi> The kynges Grammer.</note>Item, whether there be any other Grammer taught in any ſcoole within this Dioceſſe, then that which is ſet forth by the aucthoritie of king Henry theyght.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>31.</hi> The tyme of ſeruice.</note>Item, whether the ſeruice of the Church be done at due and conuenient houres.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>32.</hi> Talkers in the Church.</note>Item, whether anye haue vſed to common, tangle, and talke in the Churche in the tyme of the prayer, readyng of the Homylye, preachyng, readyng or declaryng of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>33.</hi> Hereſies.</note> whether any haue wylfully maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and defended any hereſyes, errors, or falſe opinions, contrary to the faith of Chryſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26824:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>34.</hi> Dronkardes</note> whether any be common dronkardes, ſwearers, or blaſphemers of the name of God.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>35.</hi> Adulterers.</note> whether any haue committed adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, fornication, or inceſt, or be common bawdes, or receiuers of ſuch euyll perſons, or vehemently ſuſpected of any of the premiſſes.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>36.</hi> Brawlers.</note> whether any be brawlers, ſlaunderers, chyders, ſcolders, and ſowers of diſcord betwene one perſon and another.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>37.</hi> Sorcerers.</note> whether you knowe any that do vſe charmes, ſorcery, enchauntmentes, inuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, circles, witchcraftes, ſouthſaying, or any lyke craftes or imaginations inuented by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, and ſpecially in the tyme of womens tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>38.</hi> Pulpittes.</note> whether the Churches, Pulpittes, and other neceſſaryes apperteynyng to the ſame, be ſufficiently repayred, and if they be not, in whoſe default the ſame is.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>39.</hi> Reſorters to other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note>Item, whether you knowe any, that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of theyr owne paryſhe Churche, do reſort to any other Church.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>40.</hi> Inholders.</note> whether any Inholders, or Alehouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kepers, do vſe commonly to ſell meate &amp; drynke in the tyme of common prayer, preachyng, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the Homylyes or Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26824:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>41.</hi> Diuorſe.</note> whether you knowe any to be marryed within the degrees prohibited by the lawes of God, or that be ſeperated or diuorſed without the degrees prohibited by the lawe of God, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any ſuch haue marryed agayne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>42.</hi> Priuie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes.</note>Item, whether you knowe any to haue made priuie contractes of Matrimonye, not callyng two or mo witneſſes therevnto, nor hauyng thereto the conſent of theyr parentes.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>43.</hi> Banes.</note> whether they haue maryed ſolempnly, the banes not fyrſt lawfully aſked.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>44.</hi> Erecutours</note> whether you knowe any executours or adminiſtratours of dead mens goodes, which do not duelye beſtowe ſuche of the ſayde goodes as were geuen and bequeathed, or appoynted to be diſtributed among the poore people, repayryng of hygh wayes, fyndyng of poore ſcollers, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying or poore maydens, or ſuch other lyke cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable dedes.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>45.</hi> Images.</note> whether you knowe any that kepe in theyr houſes vndefaced, any Images, Tables, Pictures, payntynges, or other monumentes of fayned and falſe miracles, pylgrimages, idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſuperſtition, and do adore them, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as haue ben ſet vp in Churches, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles, or Oratories.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>46.</hi> Bookes.</note> what Bookes of Gods Scripture you
<pb facs="tcp:26824:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->haue deliuered to be burnt, or otherwiſe deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to whom ye haue deliuered the ſame.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>47.</hi> Brybes.</note> what brybes the accuſers, promoters, perſecutors, Eccleſiaſticall iudges, and other the Commiſſioners appoynted within the ſeuerall Dioceſſe of this Realme, haue receiued by them ſelues or other, of thoſe perſons whiche were in trouble, apprehended, or impriſoned for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>48.</hi> Loſſe of goodes.</note>Item, what goodes, moueable landes, fees, offices, or promotions, hath ben wrongfully ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away in the tyme of Quene Maries raigne, from any perſon whiche fauoured the Religion nowe ſet forth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>49.</hi> How many burnt.</note>Item, howe many perſons for Religion haue dyed by fyre, famine, or otherwyſe, or haue ben impriſoned for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>50.</hi> Certificat of the dead.</note>Item, that you make a true preſentment of the number of all the perſons which dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your pariſhes, ſithen the feaſt of Saint Iohn the Baptiſt, which was in the yere of our Lorde God a thouſande fiue hundreth fiftie and eyght, vnto the ſame feaſt laſt paſt. Makyng therein a playne diſtincte declaration, howe many men, women, and men chyldren the ſame were. And the names of the men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>51.</hi> Secrete Maſſes.</note>Item, whether ye knowe any man in your
<pb facs="tcp:26824:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->paryſhe, ſecretlye or in vnlawfull conuenticles, ſay or heare Maſſe, or any other ſeruice prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the lawe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>52.</hi> Falſe ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</note>Item, whether you knowe any perſon in your Paryſhe, to be a ſlaunderer of his neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or a ſower of diſcorde betwene partie and partie, man and wyfe, parentes and theyr chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or that hath inuented, bruted, or ſet foorth any rumours,<note place="margin">Vnlawfull bookes.</note> falſe and ſedicious tales, ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or makers, bryngers, byers, ſellers, kepers, or conueyers, of any vnlawfull bookes, whiche myght ſtirre or prouoke ſedition, or mainteyne ſuperſtitious ſeruice within this Realme, or any aydours, counſaylours, procurers, or mayntey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners therevnto.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>53.</hi> Patron. Tythes. Vacation.</note>Item, whether the Churche of your paryſhe be nowe vacant or no, who is the Patrone ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, howe long it hath ben vacant, who doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the tythes, oblations, and other commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities duryng the tyme of the vacation, and by what aucthoritie, and in what eſtate the ſayde Church is at this tyme, and howe long the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or Vicar hath had that Benefice.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>54.</hi> Minſtrelles.</note> whether any Minſtrelles, or any other perſons do vſe to ſyng or ſaye any ſonges or dyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that be vyle or vncleane, and eſpeciallye in deriſion of any Godly order nowe ſet foorth and eſtablyſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26824:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>55.</hi> Letany in Englyſhe.</note>Item, whether the Letany in Englyſhe, with the Epiſtle &amp; Goſpel, which was by the Quenes highneſſe Proclamation wylled to be read to the people, were put in vſe in your Churches, and if not, who were the letters therof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>56.</hi> Diſtinct rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng.</note>Item, whether the Curates and Miniſters do leyſurely, playnely, and diſtinctly, reade the publique Prayers, Chapters, and Homylyes, as they ought to do.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Quene.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED AT LONDON IN</hi> Powles Church yarde by Richard Iugge and Iohn Cawood, Printers to the Quenes Maieſtie.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
